http://www.woodlawnhospital.com/getpage.php?name=privacy&sub=My%20Patient%20Connection

skip navigation
skip navigation
About UsOur HistoryLeadershipOur MissionOur Code of ConductHospital DirectoryMap to WoodlawnContact UsProvidersOur ProvidersMedical Staff OfficeServicesList of All ServicesFulton County Medical ClinicRobotic SurgeryRochester OrthopedicsRochester Pulmonary ServicesRochester Surgical ServicesTotal Joint Care ProgramWomen's Health ServicesWoodlawn Internal and Critical Care MedicineWoodlawn Medical ProfessionalsWoodlawn PediatricsWoodlawn Specialty ClinicWoodlawn Wound Care CenterEmploymentCareer OpportunitiesPhysician RecruitmentEmployee BenefitsBecome a VolunteerOur CommunityHR ConnectionContact Human ResourcesVisitorsPatient StoriesVisitor InformationWoodlawn FoundationWoodlawn Hospital AuxiliaryOnline Baby NurseryClasses and Events CalendarCafeteria MenuSend An E-CardSites of InterestMy Hospital PortalMy Clinic PortalPortal ApplicationPatient InformationAdvance DirectivesAuthorization to Release Health Info FormPre-RegistrationBilling and InsuranceOnline Bill PayFinancial AidHospital PricesTime of Service Co-PayNotice of Privacy PracticesComplaintsPatient Stories
The People. The Technology. Right Here At Home.
Links
Wellness NewsletterCommunity HealthHealth InformationPay Your BillPre-Register OnlineFind a PhysicianBaby NurseryCareer OpportunitiesSend an E-CardMake a DonationBecome a VolunteerClasses and EventsGift ShopContact UsPresident's MessageDocTalk
Notices of Privacy Practices for Protected Health Information
This Notice of Privacy Practices describes how we may use and disclose your protected health information to carry out treatment, payment or health care operations and for other purposes that are permitted or required by law.
It also describes your rights to access and control your protected health information. "Protected health information" is information about you, including demographic information, that may identify you and that relates to your past, present or future physical or mental health or condition and related health care services.
If you have any questions about this notice or about medical records, please contact:
Woodlawn Hospital
Health Information Management
1400 E Ninth Street
Rochester, Indiana 46975
(574) 224-1140
or Click Here to email our Privacy Officer.
We are required to abide by the terms of this Notice of Privacy Practices. We may change the terms of our notice at any time. The new notice will be effective for all protected health information that we maintain both before and after the change. Upon your request, we will provide you with any revised Notice of Privacy Practices by calling the office and requesting that a revised copy be sent to you in the mail or asking for one at the time of your next appointment.
This notice describes our Hospital's practices and that of:
Any health care professional authorized to enter information into your Hospital chart.All departments and units of the Hospital, including subsidiaries and outpatient departments of the Hospital.Any member of a volunteer group we allow to help you while you are in the hospital.All employees, staff and other Hospital personnel.All physicians who have staff privileges at the Hospital including physicians specializing in orthopedics, general surgery, anesthesiology, radiology, cardiology, pathology, etc. and who participate in an organized health care arrangement with the Hospital and have agreed to abide by the terms set forth.All these entities, sites and locations follow the terms of the notice. In addition, these entities, sites and locations may share medical information with each other for treatment, payment or Hospital operation purposes described in this notice.
Uses and Disclosures of Protected Health Information
You will be asked by the Hospital to sign this Notice of Privacy Practices. We will make a good faith effort to obtain a written acknowledgement that you received this Notice of Privacy Practices for Protected Health Information the first time we provide services to you or as soon as reasonably practicable under the circumstances.
Your protected health information may be used and disclosed by your physician, our hospital staff and others outside of our Hospital that are involved in your care and treatment for the purpose of providing health care services to you. Your protected health information may also be used and disclosed to obtain payment for your health care bills and to support the operation of the Hospital.
Following are examples of the types of uses and disclosures of your protected health care information that the Hospital is permitted to make. These examples are not meant to be exhaustive, but to describe the types of uses and disclosures that may be made by the Hospital.
Treatment
We will use and disclose your protected health information to provide, coordinate or manage your health care and any related services. This includes the coordination or management of your health care with a third party that has already obtained your permission to have access to your protected health information. We may disclose medical information about you to doctors, nurses, technicians, medical students, or other Hospital personnel who are involved in taking care of you at the Hospital. For example, a doctor treating you for a broken leg may need to know if you have diabetes because diabetes may slow the healing process. In addition, the doctor may need to tell the dietitian if you have diabetes so that we can arrange for appropriate meals.
Different departments of the Hospital also may share medical information about you in order to coordinate the different things you need, such as prescriptions, lab work and x-rays. We also may disclose medical information about you to people outside the Hospital who may be involved in your medical care after you leave the Hospital, such as family members, clergy or others we use to provide services that are part of your care. We will also disclose protected health information to other physicians who may be treating you. For example, your protected health information may be provided to a physician to whom you have been referred to ensure that the physician has the necessary information to diagnose or treat you.
In addition, we may disclose your protected health information from time-to-time to another hospital, physician or health care provider (e.g., a specialist or laboratory) who, at the request of your physician, becomes involved in your care by providing assistance with your health care diagnosis or treatment to your physician.
Payment
Your protected health information will be used, as needed, to obtain payment for your health care services. This may include certain activities that your health insurance plan may undertake before it approves or pays for the health care services we recommend for you such as: making a determination of eligibility or coverage for insurance benefits, reviewing services provided to you for medical necessity and undertaking utilization review activities. For example, obtaining approval for a hospital stay may require that your relevant protected health information be disclosed to the health plan to obtain approval for the hospital admission.
Healthcare Operations
We may use or disclose, as needed, your protected health information in order to support the business activities of the Hospital. These activities include, but are not limited to, quality assessment activities, employee review activities, training of medical students, licensing, and conducting or arranging for other business activities.
For example, we may disclose your protected health information to medical school students that see patients at the hospital. In addition, we may use a sign-in sheet at a registration desk where you will be asked to sign your name and indicate your physician. We may also call you by name in waiting rooms when your physician is ready to see you. We may use or disclose your protected health information, as necessary, to contact you to remind you of your appointment.
We will share your protected health information with third party "business associates" that perform various activities (e.g., billing, transcription services) for the practice. Whenever an arrangement between our office and a business associate involves the use or disclosure of your protected health information, we will have a written contract that contains terms that will protect the privacy of your protected health information.
We may use or disclose your protected health information, as necessary, to provide you with information about treatment alternatives or other health-related benefits and services that may be of interest to you. We may also use and disclose your protected health information for other marketing activities. For example, your name and address may be used to send you a newsletter about the Hospital and the services we offer. We may also send you information about products or services that we believe may be beneficial to you. You may contact our Privacy Contact to request that these materials not be sent to you.
We may use or disclose your demographic information and the dates that you received treatment at the Hospital, as necessary, in order to contact you for fundraising activities supported by the Hospital. If you do not want to receive these materials, please contact our Privacy Contact and request that these fundraising materials not be sent to you.
Uses and Disclosures of Protected Health Information Based Upon Your Written Authorization
Other uses and disclosures of your protected health information will be made only with your written authorization, unless otherwise permitted or required by law as described below. You may revoke this authorization, at any time, in writing, except to the extent that the Hospital has taken an action in reliance on the use or disclosure indicated in the authorization.
Other Permitted and Required Uses and Disclosures that may be made without Your Authorization or Opportunity to Object
We may use and disclose your protected health information in the following instances. You have the opportunity to agree or object to the use or disclosure of all or part of your protected health information. If you are not present or able to agree or object to the use or disclosure of the protected health information, then your physician may, using professional judgment, determine whether the disclosure is in your best interest. In this case, only the protected health information that is relevant to your health care will be disclosed.
Facility Directories
Unless you object, we will use and disclose in our facility directory your name, the location at which you are receiving care, your condition (in general terms), and your religious affiliation. All of this information, except religious affiliation, will be disclosed to people that ask for you by name. Members of the clergy will be told your religious affiliation.
Others Involved in Your Healthcare
Unless you object, we may disclose to a member of your family, a relative, a close friend or any other person you identify, your protected health information that directly relates to that person's involvement in your health care. If you are unable to agree or object to such a disclosure, we may disclose such information as necessary if we determine that it is in your best interest based on our professional judgment.
We may use or disclose protected health information to notify or assist in notifying a family member, personal representative or any other person that is responsible for your care of your location, general condition or death.
Finally, we may use or disclose your protected health information to an authorized public or private entity to assist in disaster relief efforts and to coordinate uses and disclosures to family or other individuals involved in your health care.
Emergencies
We may use or disclose your protected health information in an emergency treatment situation. If this happens, the Hospital will try to obtain your acknowledgement of our Privacy Practices as soon as reasonably practicable after the delivery of treatment. If your physician or another physician in the practice is required by law to treat you and the physician has attempted to obtain your acknowledgement, but is unable, he or she may still use or disclose your protected health information for treatment, payment, and health care operations.
Communication Barriers
We may use and disclose your protected health information if the Hospital attempts to obtain an acknowledgement of our Privacy Practices from you, but is unable to do so due to substantial communication barriers.
Other Permitted and Required Uses and Disclosures that may be made without Your Consent, Authorization or Opportunity to Object
We may use or disclose your protected health information in the following situations without your acknowledgement or authorization. These situations include:
Required By Law
We may use or disclose your protected health information to the extent that the use or disclosure is required by law. The use or disclosure will be made in compliance with the law and will be limited to the relevant requirements of the law. You will be notified, as required by law, of any such uses or disclosures.
Public Health
We may disclose your protected health information for public health activities and purposes to a public health authority that is permitted by law to collect or receive the information. The disclosure will be made for the purpose of controlling disease, injury or disability. We may also disclose your protected health information, if directed by the public health authority, to a foreign government agency that is collaborating with the public health authority.
Communicable Diseases
We may disclose your protected health information, if authorized by law, to a person who may have been exposed to a communicable disease or may otherwise be at risk of contracting or spreading the disease or condition.
Health Oversight
We may disclose protected health information to a health oversight agency for activities authorized by law, such as audits, investigations, and inspections. Oversight agencies seeking this information include government agencies that oversee the health care system, government benefit programs, other government regulatory programs and civil rights laws.
Abuse or Neglect
We may disclose your protected health information to a public health authority that is authorized by law to receive reports of child abuse or neglect. In addition, we may disclose your protected health information if we believe that you have been a victim of abuse, neglect or domestic violence to the governmental entity or agency authorized to receive such information. In this case, the disclosure will be made consistent with the requirements of applicable federal and state laws.
Food and Drug Administration
We may disclose your protected health information to a person or company required by the Food and Drug Administration to report adverse events, product defects or problems, biologic product deviations; track products; to enable product recalls; to make repairs or replacements; or to conduct post marketing surveillance, as required.
Legal Proceedings
We may disclose protected health information in the course of any judicial or administrative proceeding, in response to an order of a court or administrative tribunal (to the extent such disclosure is expressly authorized), in certain conditions in response to a subpoena, discovery request or other lawful process.
Law Enforcement
We may also disclose protected health information, so long as applicable legal requirements are met, for law enforcement purposes. These law enforcement purposes include:
(1) legal processes and otherwise required by law,(2) limited information requests for identification and location purposes,(3) pertaining to victims of a crime,(4) suspicion that death has occurred as a result of criminal conduct,(5) in the event that a crime occurs on the premises of the practice, and(6) medical emergency (not on the Hospital's premises) and it is likely that a crime has occurred.Coroners, Funeral Directors, and Organ Donation
We may disclose protected health information to a coroner or medical examiner for identification purposes, determining cause of death or for the coroner or medical examiner to perform other duties authorized by law. We may also disclose protected health information to a funeral director, as authorized by law, in order to permit the funeral director to carry out his/her duties. We may disclose such information in reasonable anticipation of death. Protected health information may be used and disclosed for cadaver organ, eye or tissue donation purposes.
Research
We may disclose your protected health information to researchers when their research has been approved by an institutional review board that has reviewed the research proposal and established protocols to ensure the privacy of your protected health information.
Criminal Activity
Consistent with applicable federal and state laws, we may disclose your protected health information if we believe that the use or disclosure is necessary to prevent or lessen a serious and imminent threat to the health or safety of a person or the public. We may also disclose protected health information if it is necessary for law enforcement authorities to identify or apprehend an individual.
Military Activity and National Security
When the appropriate conditions apply, we may use or disclose protected health information of individuals who are Armed Forces personnel:
(1) for activities deemed necessary by appropriate military command authorities;(2) for the purpose of a determination by the Department of Veterans Affairs of your eligibility for benefits; or(3) to foreign military authority if you are a member of that foreign military services.We may also disclose your protected health information to authorized federal officials for conducting national security and intelligence activities, including for the provision of protective services to the President or others legally authorized.
Workers' Compensation
Your protected health information may be disclosed by us as authorized to comply with workers' compensation laws and other similar legally established programs.
Inmates
We may use or disclose your protected health information if you are an inmate of a correctional facility and the Hospital has created or received your protected health information in the course of providing care to you.
Required Uses and Disclosures
Under the law, we must make disclosures to you and when required by the Secretary of the Department of Health and Human Services to investigate or determine our compliance with the requirements of federal regulations that protect the privacy of your protected health information.
Your Rights
Following is a statement of your rights with respect to your protected health information and a brief description of how you may exercise these rights.
You have the right to inspect and copy your protected health information. This means you may inspect and obtain a copy of protected health information about you that is contained in a designated record set for as long as we maintain the protected health information. A "designated record set" contains medical and billing records and any other records that the Hospital uses for making decisions about you.Under federal law, however; you may not inspect or copy the following records: psychotherapy notes; information compiled in reasonable anticipation of, or use in, a civil, criminal, or administrative action or proceeding; and protected health information that is subject to law that prohibits access to protected health information. Depending on the circumstances, a decision to deny access may be reviewable. In some circumstances, you may have a right to have this decision reviewed. Please contact our Privacy Officer if you have questions about access to your medical record.
You have the right to request a restriction of your protected health information. This means you may ask us not to use or disclose any part of your protected health information for the purposes of treatment, payment or healthcare operations. You may also request that any part of your protected health information not be disclosed to family members or friends who may be involved in your care or for notification purposes as described in this Notice of Privacy Practices. Your request must state the specific restriction requested and to whom you want the restriction to apply.The Hospital is not required to agree to a restriction that you may request. If the Hospital believes it is in your best interest to permit use and disclosure of your protected health information, your protected health information will not be restricted. If the Hospital does agree to the requested restriction, we may not use or disclose your protected health information in violation of that restriction unless it is needed to provide emergency treatment. With this in mind, please discuss any restriction you wish to request with us.
You may request a restriction by submitting a written request to our Privacy Officer.
You have the right to request to receive confidential communications from us by alternative means or at an alternative location. We will accommodate reasonable requests. We may also condition this accommodation by asking you for information as to how payment will be handled or specification of an alternative address or other method of contact. We will not request an explanation from you as to the basis for the request. Please make this request in writing to our Privacy Officer.You may have the right to have the Hospital amend your protected health information. This means you may request an amendment of protected health information about you in a designated record set for as long as we maintain this information. In certain cases, we may deny your request for an amendment. If we deny your request for amendment, you have the right to file a statement of disagreement with us and we may prepare a rebuttal to your statement and will provide you with a copy of any such rebuttal. Please contact our Privacy Officer if you have questions about amending your medical record.You have the right to receive an accounting of certain disclosures we have made, if any, of your protected health information. This right applies to disclosures for purposes other than treatment, payment or healthcare operations as described in this Notice of Privacy Practices. It excludes disclosures we may have made to you, for a facility directory, to family members or friends involved in your care, or for notification purposes. You have the right to receive specific information regarding these disclosures that occurred after April 14, 2003. You may request a shorter timeframe. The right to receive this information is subject to certain exceptions, restrictions and limitations.You have the right to obtain a paper copy of this notice from us, upon request, even if you have agreed to accept this notice electronically.Complaints
You may complain to us or to the Office of Civil Rights (OCR) if you believe your privacy rights have been violated by us. You may file a complaint with us by notifying our Privacy Officer of your complaint. We will not retaliate against you for filing a complaint.
You may contact our Privacy Officer at (574) 224-1142 for further information about the complaint process.
1400 East Ninth Street | Rochester, Indiana 46975 | (574) 223-3141
©2020 FastHealth Corporation
Terms
Privacy
